Guide to the Lewis E. White Papers and Memorabilia
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lewis E. White papers and memorabilia
circa 1895-1930s
SC1016
White, Lewis E., 1894-1919.
0.75 Linear feet (2 boxes)
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Materials were the gift of Wendy A. Nipper, 2010.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical note
Lewis E. White studied mechanical engineering at Stanford University from 1913 to 1917, when he joined the U.S. Army, serving overseas in World War I. He died in Germany in 1919.
Scope and Contents note
Collection includes family photographs, studio portraits of White, photograph album largely pertaining to his time at Stanford, photographs of his gravesite, two letters by White written while serving in World War I, and other letters pertaining to White’s service and death.
Access Terms
Stanford University -- General subdivision--Students.;; Stanford University. Memorial Church; World War, 1914-1918.
Collection Contents
- Photographs, circa 1895-1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  4 x 6 sepia tone double image baby picture labeled “Roberts, Chico, Cal.” circa 1895; 4 x 5 glossy photo of Lewis on horseback; 4 x 6 portrait of Lewis White (in dress with wide white collar and wide cuffs); 3 x 4 glossy portrait approx. 1902 - 1904 (8 – 10 yrs. old); 7 x 5 Lewis E. with his mother Nellie (Morse) White in Chico.
- Photographs, 1909-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  3” oval portrait of Lewis by Hemminger 1909; 5 x 7 (not including mounting) family portrait by Hemminger of Chico, California, (seated L to R) Harry D. White and Nellie M. White, parents, and (standing L to R) Marie Cecil and Lewis Edmund dated March 2, 1910; 3 x 5 sepia portrait of Lewis White in folder labeled “Valentine, Redding Cal.” Circa 1913; 4 x 6 sepia portrait (by Davey) of Lewis White in folder, circa 1914; Lewis E. standing with hat in right hand, palm trees in background; Lewis E. leaning against oak tree, reportedly at Stanford.
- Photographs, military (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Lewis E. in WWI uniform topped with college sweater, standing with his mother, Nellie M. White; Lewis E. in 3 variations of WWI uniform; Lewis E. in uniform in outdoor setting, reclining by tree; Lewis E. in uniform (on left in photo) in tent office with another man seated to his left.
- Photographs, gravesite (Box 1, Folder 4)
  5 x 7 photo at decorated gravesite of Lewis E. White, Coblenz, Germany. Names enscribed on the back are: J. H. Daumbacher, Eddie Einstein, Olsen, Foster Reber, John Horn, Joe Yarobough; 2 photos, 3 x 4, of the marked grave; 1 photo, 3 x 4, possibly of decorated gravesite.
- Photograph album, 1913-1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes images of northern California – Chico area, freshman Lewis E. White, Stanford Stadium events, bonfire 1913 & 1914 Stanford vs. Cal Berkeley; 1913 & 1914 Rush, 1914 Encina Club, and Stanford campus.
- Letters by Lewis E. White, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  2 pg. letter from Lewis to Mrs. Hosmer, family friend in the Chico, California area, dated January 28, 1919 from Coblenz, Germany. The postscript was added after the Hosmer’s received Lewis’s letter. Note it took almost a month from the original date for delivery of this letter. 2 pg. letter: Soldiers Mail of February 02, 1919, Coblenz, Germany from Lewis to his sister, Marie C. White in Redding, Shasta County, California. Lewis makes reference in this letter to having sent a letter to the Hosmers. With envelope and enclosure of 1 piece of French money.
- Letters concerning Lewis E. White, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  1 pg. letter dated from Coblenz June 1, 1919 by Walter Essler to Mrs. White, Lewis’s mother. 1 pg. carbon copy of letter dated July 22, 1919 from Lewis E. White’s Uncle George P. Morse on letterhead from Butte County Savings Bank, Chico replying to Private Walter Essler’s letter of June 1, 1919. Letter from C. A. Thurman dated August 20, 1919, Provo, Utah, to Mr. Morse – presumed to be Lewis’s Uncle George P. Morse. 1 pg. letter to C. A. Thurman of Provo, Utah dated August 23, 1919. Probably sent by Lewis’s Uncle George P. Morse. Letter from Vera Marston dated September 2, 1920, San Francisco, California, to Miss Marie White, Lewis’s sister. Vera Marston was a nurse on duty at Evacuation Hospital #14 in Coblenz, Germany where Lewis died. With envelope. 1 pg. letter, undated, from The American Red Cross regarding photographs of the graves of American dead.
- Certificates, 1914-1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Certificate from Army of the United States of America stating, “Lewis E. White died with honor in the service of his country February 10, 1919”; and certificate of membership in Theta Xi Fraternity [Stanford] September 19, 1914.
- Genealogy of the Morse, Lewis, White families prepared by Wendy Alice Hamma Nipper, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Digital copies of photos, inventory, genealogies (2 discs) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Memorabilia: Sterling silver teaspoon with Hooker Oak, Chico engraved in the bowl; initials LEW engraved on handle; 1905 engraved on reverse of handle (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2014-070
  - 1922 baccalaureate service program, 2 Bear Photo Co. photographs of Stanford Memorial Church, 1 photograph of Lewis E. White (scanned portrait), and 1 of Lewis E. White in front of Stanford Theta Xi house.), 1913-1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)